A Finding Aid to the Abbott Handerson Thayer and Thayer Family Papers, 1851-1999 (bulk 1881-1950), in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Writings, 1888-1945; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; (Box 3-4; 0.8 linear feet)
  - Writings by Abbott Handerson Thayer, circa 1890-1918; 3.1; Archival Resource Key
    - Notes & Essays on Concealing Coloration in Uniforms & Warships, circa 1915-1918; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Notes & Essays on Concealing Coloration in Uniforms & Warships, circa 1915-1918; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Essay, "Restoration: The Doom of Works of Art", 1917; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Typescript, "Restoration of Pictures", circa 1910s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Typescript, "Restoration of Pictures", circa 1910s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Typescript, "Restoration of Pictures", circa 1910s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Draft Letters to the Editor of The Auk, 1916-1917; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Notes & Essays on Various Subjects, circa 1901-1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Notes & Essays on Various Subjects, circa 1901-1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Notes & Essays on Various Subjects, circa 1901-1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Notes & Essays on Various Subjects, circa 1901-1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Writings by Others, 1888-1989; 3.2; Archival Resource Key
    This subseries contains writings by the Thayer family and writings by scholars, primarily about Abbott Handerson Thayer. Included are writings by Emma Thayer, such as a manuscript for a story entitiled "Ernest" and two poems, and Mary Thayer's diary and corresponding hand-made calendar, written when she was ten years old. Writings by Gladys Thayer Reasoner include a brief biographical sketch of her father, a biography of her son, Allen Reasoner, who died in 1943 in a plane crash, and stories and other writings she wrote as a young girl.
    Writings by others about Abbott Thayer include a draft manuscript by Nancy Bell, wife of artist Arthur Bell, about Thayer's book on concealing coloration. This series also contains writings by unidentified authors, such as draft writings about George Gray Barnard, possibly written by David or Gladys Thayer Reasoner, and miscellaneous writings and poetry by others. Folders are arranged by author and title of work, if known, and chronologically within each folder.
    - Emma Beach Thayer, "Ernest", circa 1900; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Emma Beach Thayer, Poetry, circa 1910; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Mary Thayer, Diary and Calendar, 1888; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Gladys Thayer Reasoner, Biographical Sketch of Abbott H. Thayer, circa 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Gladys Thayer Reasoner, Biography of Allen Reasoner, "One Out of Fifty", circa 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Gladys Thayer Reasoner, Biography of Allen Reasoner, Draft Versions, circa 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 45-47)
    - Gladys Thayer Reasoner, Miscellaneous Writings, circa 1897; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Sidney Allen, "Abbott Handerson Thayer: An Appreciation of His Work", circa 1920s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Nancy Bell, "A Painter Naturalist and His Son", circa 1909; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - William Dutcher, "Report of the A. O. U. Committee on the Protection of North American Birds for the Year 1903", Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Elizabeth Walmsley, "A Preliminary Investigation into the Painting Techniquest of Abbott Handerson Thayer", 1988-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Unknown Author, Notes for a Book on Abbott H. Thayer, circa 1920s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Unknown Author, Lecture on Rembrandt and Reubens, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Unknown Author, Writings about George Grey Barnard, circa 1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Miscellaneous Writings by Others, circa 1890-1920; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous Poetry, circa 1900-1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Estate Papers, 1921-1954; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; (Box 4; 0.5 linear feet)
  This series contains the estate papers for Abbott Handerson Thayer, who died in 1921 and Emma Beach Thayer, who died in 1924. Much of material consists of correspondence between David Reasoner, Executor of both estates, and others regarding financial and legal matters. Correspondence of note is with Mary and Gerald Thayer regarding their inheritance, and with E. & A. Milch, Inc. and William Macbeth, Inc. regarding the sale of artwork. Also found are financial and legal documents, forms, lists and notes, and Emma Thayer's will and drafts. Some of the financial account statements and a ledger book have not been scanned.
  Items are arranged chronologically within each folder.
  - Estate Papers of Abbott H. Thayer and Emma B. Thayer, 1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Estate Papers of Abbott H. Thayer and Emma B. Thayer, 1922-1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Estate Papers of Abbott H. Thayer and Emma B. Thayer, 1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Estate Papers of Abbott H. Thayer and Emma B. Thayer, 1925; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Estate Papers of Abbott H. Thayer and Emma B. Thayer, 1925; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Estate Papers of Abbott H. Thayer and Emma B. Thayer, 1926; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Estate Papers of Abbott H. Thayer and Emma B. Thayer, 1927; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Estate Papers of Abbott H. Thayer and Emma B. Thayer, 1928; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Estate Papers of Abbott H. Thayer and Emma B. Thayer, 1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Estate Papers of Abbott H. Thayer and Emma B. Thayer, 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Estate Papers of Abbott H. Thayer and Emma B. Thayer, 1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Estate Papers of Abbott H. Thayer and Emma B. Thayer, 1932; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Estate Papers of Abbott H. Thayer and Emma B. Thayer, 1933-1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Estate Papers of Abbott H. Thayer and Emma B. Thayer, 1937-1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Estate Papers of Abbott H. Thayer and Emma B. Thayer, 1939-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Estate Papers of Abbott H. Thayer and Emma B. Thayer, 1941-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Emma Beach Thayer Last Will and Testament, 1923, 1926; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Estate Account Statements, Kingston Trust Company, 1927-1932; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 20-21)
  - Estate Bills, 1922-1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 22-23)
  - Ledger Book for Emma Thayer Estate, 1924-1925; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Other Financial Records, 1889-1957; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; (Box 4; 7 folders)
  This series contains a small amount of Thayer and Reasoner family financial records not directly related to the estates of Abbott or Emma Thayer. Most of this series has not been scanned.
  - Account Statements, 1924-1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Bills & Receipts, 1889-1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Liberty Bonds, Cheshire National Bank, 1919-1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Ledger, 1923-1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Ledger kept by Emma Beach Thayer, 1915-1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Ledger kept by David Reasoner, 1921-1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - David Reasoner Bethesda Country Club Membership, 1948-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Legal Records, 1891-1927; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; (Box 4; 4 folders)
  Legal records include a copy of the patent office record given to Gerome Brush and Abbott Handerson Thayer for the "process of treating the outsides of ships & for making them less visible." Also included in that folder is a contract handwritten by Thayer giving Brush claim to use of the original invention. Other documents in this series are legal agreements, including a draft agreement among landowners in Dublin, New Hampshire to create a nature reservation, and deeds of property belonging to Abbott Thayer and Emma Beach Thayer. Also found is a map of the property owned by Thayer and surrounding properties in Dublin.
  - Patent Documents, 1902, 1911; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Legal Agreements, 1908-1927; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Deeds of Property, 1891-1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Map of Thayer Property, Dublin, New Hampshire, 1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Printed Material, 1851, 1896-1999; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; (Box 4-5; 0.4 linear feet)
  Printed material includes two books, an alphabet book belonging to Abbott Thayer which he inscribed and gave to his daughter Mary, and a bound article written by Theodore Roosevelt in response to Thayer's book on concealing coloration. The article was originally published in the Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History, volume XXX. Also found are newspaper and magazine clippings about Abbott Thayer, about his artwork and exhibitions, and about the Reasoner family. Exhibition announcements and catalogs are for exhibitions by Thayer, his daughter Gladys Thayer Reasoner, and group exhibitions. Other material in this series is about the Woodstock Playhouse, for which David Reasoner was the director, and includes news clippings, programs and newsletters, and the publication Hue and Cry.
  - Book, Illustrated Alphabet of Animals, 1851; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Book, Revealing and Concealing Coloration in Birds and Mammals, by Theodore Roosevelt, 1911, Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Clippings, 1900-1916; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Clippings, 1919-1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Clippings, 1951-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Clippings, 1981-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Clippings, 1993-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Clippings about Woodstock Playhouse, circa 1929-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1896; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1911; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1919-1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1922-1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1930-1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1949-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Newsletters & Event Calendars, 1980-1983, 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Newsletters & Programs from Woodstock, New York, 1928-1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Hue and Cry Newspaper, 1925, 1928, 1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1895, 1914-circa 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Photographs, circa 1861-1933; Series 8; Archival Resource Key; (Box 5, MGP 2; 0.2 linear feet)
  This series contains photographs of Abbott H. Thayer, including two portraits of him, a photo of him with a group of people (possibly at Gerald Thayer's wedding), and a photograph of his plaster death mask. Also found are photographs of Thayer's studio, some of which include the painting he was working on at the time, his son Gerald, and other models. There are photographs of Thayer's home in Dublin, New Hampshire. Additional photographs are of his wife, Emma Beach Thayer, Ralph Waldo Emerson, and one of his former student Rockwell Kent painting outdoors. Also found are numerous photographs of unidentified people, most likely members of the Thayer family, and a few photographs of artwork by Thayer.
  - Photographs of Abbott H. Thayer, circa 1861, 1900, 1915; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Thayer's Studio, circa 1895; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of Thayer's Home, Dublin, New Hampshire, circa 1905; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Photographs of Emma Beach Thayer, circa 1870, 1889; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Photographs of Gladys Thayer Reasoner & Family (Photocopies), circa 1915, 1933; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Photographs of Lyman and Grace Reasoner, circa 1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Photographs of Ralph Waldo Emerson, circa 1860; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Photograph of Rockwell Kent, circa 1905; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Unidentified Portraits, circa 1860-1890; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Unidentified Tintype Portraits, circa 1870-1890; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 14-15)
  - Glass Plate Negative of Unidentified Man, circa 1890; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 16)
    Scope and Contents
    (1 glass plate negative housed in MGP 2)
  - Glass Plate Negative, Archival Resource Key; 1 Glass negative (Box MGP 2)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1895; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Tintype Photograph of The Sisters, circa 1884; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Original Frame for Photograph of The Sisters, circa 1884; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Artwork, 1887 - circa 1940s; Series 9; Archival Resource Key; (Box 5-6, 8; 0.2 linear feet)
  This series includes two drawings by Abbott Thayer, one depicting an angel and modeled by his daughter Mary. Also found is a large amount of artwork by children, including drawings by Gerald Thayer and other unidentified drawings and paintings, probably by Mary, Gerald, and Gladys Thayer, animal cutouts by Jean Reasoner Plunket, and other small painted cutout figures by an unknown artist. Also found are two sketchbooks, one belonging to David Reasoner, and the other probably belonging to his daughter, Jean Reasoner Plunket.
  - Drawings by Abbott Handerson Thayer, 1887, 1912; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Artwork by Gerald Thayer, 1889; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Artwork by Unidentified Children (probably Mary, Gerald, and Gladys Thayer), circa 1890-1900; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Artwork by Unidentified Children (probably Mary, Gerald, and Gladys Thayer), circa 1890-1900; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Painted Cutout Figures, circa 1904; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - David Reasoner Sketchbook, circa 1910; Archival Resource Key; (See Box 8) (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Animal Cutouts by Jean Reasoner Plunket, circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Sketchbook (possibly belonging to Jean Reasoner Plunket), circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - David Reasoner Sketchbook, circa 1910; Archival Resource Key; (See also Box 6, folder 4) (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Scrapbook, circa 1910-1920; Series 10; Archival Resource Key; (Box 7; 0.3 linear feet)
  This large scrapbook, compiled by David Reasoner, includes photographs and printed reproductions of paintings by Abbott Thayer, as well as a few newspaper clippings about his artwork. The scrapbook also includes a few notations listing the current owners of the paintings.
  - Scrapbook about Thayer Artwork, circa 1910-1920; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 1)